Guide to the Margaret S. Mahler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Presentation Files, 1930-1984; Series II; 14 linear feet (35 boxes)
  - "Important Aspects of Child Development" Hudson Guild Community Center [Paper], 1953 November 11 (Box 31, Folder 726)
  - "Self Induced Failure: a Mechanism of Defence" by Edrita Fried, Ph.D. Postgraduate Center for Psychotherapy [Discussion], 1953 November 17 (Box 31, Folder 727)
  - "Loss and Restitution" by G. Rochlin, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1953 November 24 (Box 31, Folder 728)
  - "Some Observations on Disturbances of the Ego in a Case of Infantile Psychosis" by M. Mahler, M.D., and P. Elkisch, M.D. Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1953 (Box 31, Folder 729)
  - "Clinical Consequences of Grave Marital Discord Upon Child Development" Psychiatric Forum Group, Inc. [Paper], 1954 January 20 (Box 31, Folder 730)
  - "Psychotic Disturbances in Children" by M. Mahler, M.D., and K. Prescott, M.D. Connecticut Postgraduate Seminar in Psychiatry and Neurology [Paper], 1954 March 22 (Box 31, Folder 731)
  - "Psychotic Disturbances in Children: Early Infantile Psychosis" Baltimore Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1954 March 27 (Box 31, Folder 732)
  - "On Normal and Pathological Symbiosis" by M. Mahler, M.D., and K. Prescott, M.D. Baltimore Psychiatric Institute [Paper], 1954 March 27 (Box 31, Folder 733)
  - "Infantile Neurosis" New York Psychoanalytic Society and Institute at Arden House [Discussion], 1954 May 8 (Box 31, Folder 734)
  - Technical Meeting With Anna Freud Philadelphia Association for Psychoanalysis [Discussion], 1954 May 10 (Box 31, Folder 735)
  - Kanner, Despert, Lourie, and Lowry; papers presented at "Symposium of Psychopathology of Child" American Psychopathological Association [Discussion], 1954 June 4-5 (Box 31, Folder 736)
  - "Tics and Other Disturbances of Motility" Western Psychiatric Institute and Clinic [Paper], 1954 June 7 (Box 31, Folder 737)
  - "Contribution to Problem of Pregenital Character Disorders" by I. Silbermann New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1954 November 16 (Box 31, Folder 738)
  - "Neutralization and Sublimation: Observations on Young Children" American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1954 December 4 (Box 31, Folder 739)
  - "A Contribution to the Origin of Individualization" by K. M. Wolf American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1954 December (Box 32, Folder 740-742)
  - "An Approach to the Relation Between Concept and Content in Psychoanalytic Theory" by E. Zetzel, M.D. New York Psychiatric Society [Discussion], 1955 January 25 (Box 32, Folder 743)
  - Genetic Dynamics and Restitutive Aspects of Symbiotic Child Psychosis" by M. Mahler, M.D. and B. Gosliner, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1955 February 22 (Box 32, Folder 744-746")
  - "The Drive to Become Both Sexes" by L. Kubie, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1955 March 15 (Box 32, Folder 747)
  - "Therapy Approaches in Childhood Schizophrenia" American Psychiatric Association [Paper], 1955 May 12 (Box 33, Folder 748)
  - "The Autistic Child in Adolescence" by L. Eisenberg, M.D. American Psychiatric Association [Discussion], 1955 May 13 (Box 33, Folder 749)
  - "Symbiosis and Individuation" International Psychoanalytical Congress [Paper], 1955 July 25-28 (Box 33, Folder 750-752)
  - "Ego-Deviation and Concept of Schizophrenia" by D. Berrs, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1955 October 25 (Box 33, Folder 753)
  - Panel-On Sleep Disturbances in Children American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1955 December 1-4 (Box 33, Folder 754)
  - "Clinical Consequences of Grave Marital Disorder Upon Child Development"by M. Mahler, M.D., and R. Rabinovitch, M.D., 1955 (Box 33, Folder 755)
  - "Trauma, Dependency, and Transference" by M. Stern, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1956 February 28 (Box 33, Folder 756)
  - "Aggression, Hostility, and Guilt in Childhood" Connecticut Postgraduate Seminar in Psychiatry and Neurology [Paper], 1956 March 19 (Box 33, Folder 757)
  - Introductory Remarks Ernst Jones Dinner [Speech], 1956 April 22 (Box 33, Folder 758)
  - "The Classification and Treatment of Childhood Psychosis" by M. Mahler, M.D. and C. Settlage, M.D. American Psychiatric Association [Paper], 1956 May 3 (Box 33, Folder 759)
  - "The Ego and Mechanisms of Defense" Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Lectures], 1956 May 28 (Box 33, Folder 760)
  - "Children's Forum Discussion" King's County Hospital [Discussion], 1956 November 2 (Box 33, Folder 761)
  - "On Infantile Psychosis" Mental Health Services, Virgin Islands [Lecture], 1957 February 14 (Box 34, Folder 762)
  - "Psychotherapy of Children-Principles and Misconceptions" Albert Einstein College of Medicine [Paper, not given], 1957 March 14 (Box 34, Folder 763)
  - "Psychotic States in Children" Postgraduate Training Facility [Paper], 1957 March 25 (Box 34, Folder 764)
  - "Clinical Contributions to the Problem of Identity" Northwest Clinic of Psychiatry and Neurology, San Francisco [Paper], 1957 April 1, 8 (Box 34, Folder 765-766)
  - "On Infantile Psychosis" Philadelphia Society for Protective Techniques [Paper], 1957 April 20 (Box 34, Folder 767)
  - "On Infantile Psychosis" Albert Einstein College of Medicine [Paper], 1957 April 26 (Box 34, Folder 768)
  - "On Two Crucial Phases of Integration Concerning Problems of Identity (Separation Individuation and Bisexual Identification) Panel on Problems of Identity [American Psychoanalytic Association] [Papers], 1957 May (Box 34, Folder 769-771)
  - "On Two Crucial Phases of Integration Concerning Problems of Identity (Separation-Individuation and Bisexual Identification) Panel on Problems of Identity [American Psychoanalytic Association] [Paper and Drafts], 1957 May (Box 35, Folder 772-776)
  - "On Infantile Psychosis" University of Michigan, Ann Arbor [Paper], 1957 June (Box 35, Folder 777)
  - "Autism and Symbiosis-Two Extreme Disturbances of Identity" International Psychoanalytical Association [Paper], 1957 July 29 (Box 35, Folder 778)
  - "Ernst Kris and the Gifted Adolescent Project" by Loomie, Rosen, and Stein, M.D.'s Ernst Kris Memorial Meeting [Discussion], 1957 September 24 (Box 35, Folder 779)
  - "Anna Freud Training Program" Marianne Kris' Apartment [Discussion], 1957 September 26 (Box 35, Folder 780)
  - "Autism and Symbiosis" Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1957 October 16 (Box 35, Folder 781)
  - "A Preliminary Report of Psychophysiological Studies of the Neonate" by W. Bridger, M.D., and F. Reiser, M.D. New York Divisional Meeting of the American Psychiatric Association [Discussion], 1957 November 17 (Box 35, Folder 782)
  - "On Transference" by P. Greenacre, M.D. American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1957 December 7 (Box 35, Folder 783)
  - "Toward an Understanding of Physical Nucleus of Some Defense Reactions" by P. Greenacre, M.D. New York Psychoanalytical Society [Discussion], 1958 January 28 (Box 36, Folder 784)
  - "Borderline States in Childhood and Adolescence" by E. Geleerd, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1958 February 25 (Box 36, Folder 785)
  - "An Approach to the Investigation of Childhood Schizophrenia" by Wlm. Goldfarb, M. D. American Orthopsychiatric Association [Discussion], 1958 March 7 (Box 36, Folder 786)
  - "Community Mental Health Service in a Settlement House-Advantages, Specific Value" by M. Mahler, M.D. [Paper], 1958 March 7 (Box 36, Folder 787)
  - "The 'Influencing Machine' in Light of the Psychotic Child's Body-Image Development" by P. Elkisch, M.D., and M. Mahler, M.D. [Paper], 1958 December 6 (Box 36, Folder 788)
  - "On Infantile Precursors of the Influencing Machine'" by P. Elkisch, M.D. and M. Mahler, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1959 April 14 (Box 36, Folder 789-791)
  - Panel on Psychosomatic Diseases in Children and Adolescents American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1959 April 24 (Box 36, Folder 792)
  - "The Normal Symbiotic Relationship Between Infant and Mother and its Disturbances" Albert Einstein Medical College [Lecture], 1959 21 May (Box 36, Folder 793)
  - Child Analysis Meeting, B. Gosliner, M.D. Presentation New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1959 June 17 (Box 36, Folder 794)
  - "On 'Psychotic Object Relationships' and Differentiation" International Congress of Psycho-Analysis [Paper], 1959 July 28 (Box 36, Folder 795)
  - "On the 'Symbiotic Syndrome' in Infantile Psychosis" by M. Mahler, M.D., and M. Furer, M.D. Indiana University [Paper], 1960 April 20 (Box 36, Folder 796)
  - "Observations on a Research Decision Regarding the 'Symbiotic Syndrome' in Infantile Psychosis" by M. Mahler, M.D., and M. Furer, M.D. Pan-American Medical Conference [Paper], 1960 May 3 (Box 36, Folder 797)
  - "Sadness and Grief Concomitant With the Loss and Restoration of the Symbiotic Love Object" Harvard Medical School, Child Psychiatry Unit [Paper], 1960 October 22 (Box 37, Folder 798)
  - "Clinical and Follow-up Study of the Tic Syndrome in Children" by M. Mahler, M.D., J. A. Luke, M.D., and W. Daltroff, M.D. Lenox Hill Hospital Clinical Conference [Paper], 1961 March 9 (Box 37, Folder 799)
  - Untitled, by A. Weil, M.D. American Academy of Child Psychiatry [Notes], 1961 April 10 (Box 37, Folder 800)
  - "Motility Disturbances in Childhood Psychosis" by R. Prall, M.D. American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1961 May 5 (Box 37, Folder 801)
  - "Some Aspects of Transference Resistance in Puberty" by S. Brody, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1961 June 13 (Box 37, Folder 802)
  - "Psychoanalytic Research" Panel-Mahler, Chair International Psychoanalytical Congress [Notes], 1961 July (Box 37, Folder 803)
  - "On Infantile Psychosis" Albert Einstein Medical College [Paper], 1961 November 21 (Box 37, Folder 804)
  - "Classical Forms of Neurosis in Infancy and Early Childhood"-Panel American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion-Remarks], 1961 December 8 (Box 37, Folder 805-806)
  - The Ego and its Mechanism of Defense" Albert Einstein College of Medicine-Fellow's Seminar [Paper], 1962 February 21 (Box 37, Folder 807)
  - "On Infantile Psychosis" [?] Athens, Greece [Paper], 1962 March 27 (Box 37, Folder 808)
  - Untitled Albert Einstein College of Medicine-Fellow's Seminar [Discussion], 1962 March 20 (Box 37, Folder 809)
  - "Report on Research by Dr. Margaret S. Mahler and Co-workers at the Master's Children's Center" New York Regional Group of the American Academy of Child Psychiatry [Paper], 1962 April 23 (Box 38, Folder 810)
  - "Notes on Advances in Child Analysis" Menninger Foundation (presented to Anna Freud) [Paper], 1962 August 29 (Box 38, Folder 811)
  - "On Intermittent Child Analysis" Panel on Advances in Child Analysis Menninger Foundation [Paper], 1962 September 22 (Box 38, Folder 812-813)
  - "Thoughts about Development and Individuation" Abraham A. Brill Memorial Lecture New York Psychoanalytical Society [Paper], 1962 September 22 (Box 38, Folder 814)
  - "Analysis Terminable and Interminable" by S. Freud Albert Einstein College of Medicine-Fellow's Seminar [Paper], 1961, 1962 (Box 38, Folder 815)
  - "On-going Research" Workshop American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1963 May 4 (Box 38, Folder 816)
  - "The Nature of Dreaming," by W.C. Dement, M.D. Lee B. Jenkins Memorial Lecture University of North Carolina [Notes], 1963 March 27 (Box 38, Folder 817)
  - "Thoughts about Separation-Individuation" Washington Psychoanalytic Institute [Lecture], 1963 October 26 (Box 38, Folder 818)
  - "Studies of the Process of Normal Separation-Individuation: The Sub-Phase" Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1963 November 15 (Box 39, Folder 819)
  - "Depression in a Pre-Puberty-Age Girl" by R. Prall, M.D. Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1964, February 1, 2 (Box 39, Folder 820)
  - "On Early Infantile Psychosis"-Bellevue Paper New York University School of Medicine Department of Psychiatry and Neurology [Paper], 1964 February 17 (Box 39, Folder 821-823)
  - "Introductory Remarks to the Film: Studies of the Process of Normal Separation-Individuation" New York Council of Child Psychiatry [Paper], 1964 February 20 (Box 39, Folder 824)
  - "On Early Infantile Psychosis" Hadassah University Hospital Hadassah Medical Organization [Paper], 1964 March 24 (Box 39, Folder 825)
  - "On the Mother-Child Interaction During the Separation-Individuation Phase-The Sub-Phase" by M. Mahler, M.D., and K. La Perrier, Ph.d. American Orthopsychiatric Association [Paper], 1964 March 25 (Box 39, Folder 826)
  - "On the Significance of the Normal Separation-Individuation Phase with Reference to Research in Symbiotic Child Psychosis (with Film Illustration) Israel Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1964 March 25 (Box 39, Folder 827)
  - Untitled Kris Study Group-Lowenstein Section New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1964 October 20 (Box 39, Folder 828-829)
  - "Considerations on 'The Development of Symbiosis, Symbiotic Psychosis, and the Nature of Separation Anxiety'" by I. Hyman Weiland, M.D. [Discussion], 1964 December 4 (Box 40, Folder 830)
  - Comment on Dr. Mahler's Paper by J. R. Arraico Mexico [Discussion], 1964 (Box 40, Folder 831)
  - "On Early Infantile Psychosis (The Symbiotic and Autistic Syndrome) McGill University, Montreal, Quebec [Paper], 1965 February 4 (Box 40, Folder 832)
  - "On the Significance of the Separation-Individuation Phase for Depression" Research Conference of the Depressive Group of Illnesses, Panel IV McGill University, Montreal, Quebec [Paper], 1965 February 6 (Box 40, Folder 833)
  - Unititled Research Group of the Depressive Group of Illnesses McGill University, Montreal, Quebec [Conference Minutes], 1965 February 6 (Box 40, Folder 834)
  - Untitled Parent-Loss Workshop Chicago Institute for Psychanalysis [Discussion], 1965 February 23 (Box 40, Folder 835)
  - "Some Preliminary Notes on the Development of Basic Moods, Including Depression" Chicago Institute for Psychoanalysis [Paper], 1965 February 23 (Box 40, Folder 836)
  - "On Early Infantile Psychosis (The Symbiotic and Autistic Syndromes) Chicago Institute for Psychoanalysis [Paper], 1965 February 24 (Box 40, Folder 837-838)
  - Untitled Child Analysis Meeting Chicago Institute for Psychoanalysis [Discussion], 1965 February 24 (Box 40, Folder 839)
  - "The Selected Papers of Dr. Margaret S. Mahler" Discussion Group Number Nine American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1965 April 29 (Box 40, Folder 840)
  - "Further Studies of the Separation-Individuation Process" Council Child Development Center [Paper], 1965 May 19 (Box 41, Folder 841)
  - Untitled Conference on Theory and Technique of Child Analysis-Transference Seminar Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Seminar], 1965 May 21 (Box 41, Folder 842)
  - "Preliminary Notes on the Development of Basic Moods, Including Depression", 1965 May (Box 41, Folder 843)
  - Untitled Downstate Child Study Group [Paper], 1965 June 7 (Box 41, Folder 844)
  - "On the Development of Moods" Essex County, NJ, Psychiatric Community [Lecture], 1965 September 22 (Box 41, Folder 845)
  - "Reality Constancy-A Preliminary Note" by J. Frosch, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Institute [Discussion], 1965 October 12 (Box 41, Folder 846)
  - "On the Development of Basic Moods" Second Annual Josephine Pall and Kathryn Bobbins Memorial Lecture North Shore Child Guidance Clinic Nassau Academy of Medicine [Paper], 1966 March 9 (Box 41, Folder 847)
  - "Development of Defenses From Biological and Symbiotic Precursors Adaptive and Maladaptive Aspects" American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1966 May 6 (Box 41, Folder 848)
  - "Problems of Overidealization of the Analyst and Analysis" by P. Greenacre, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1966 May 11 (Box 41, Folder 849)
  - "On the Development of Moods" Fairfield Hills Hospital, CT [Paper], 1966 July (Box 41, Folder 850)
  - "Transference in Child Analysis" Second Pan-American Congress for Psychoanalysis [Paper-did not attend], 1966 August 1-4 (Box 41, Folder 851)
  - "Problems of Overidealization of the Analyst and Analysis" by P. Greenacre, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1966 October 11 (Box 41, Folder 852-853)
  - "Notes on the Development of Basic Moods" Washington Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1966 November 17 (Box 42, Folder 854)
  - "Child Development and the Curriculum"-Panel of C.O.P.E. on the Psychoanalytic Curriculum American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1966 December 16 (Box 42, Folder 855)
  - "Observations on Adaptation and Defense InStatu Nascendi: Developmental Precursors in the First Two Years of Life, with Film Illustrations" New York Psychoanalytic Society, Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1967 March 14, April 19 (Box 42, Folder 856)
  - Presentation by J. Alexis Burland, M.D. Visiting Analyst Case Conference [Discussion], 1967 April 19 (Box 42, Folder 857)
  - "On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation" American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper-plenary address], 1967 May 7 (Box 42, Folder 858-859)
  - Castration Anxiety and the Body Ego by L. Börge Löfgren, M.D. International Psycho-Analytical Association [Discussion], 1967 July 27 (Box 42, Folder 860)
  - "On Human Symbiosis" Tele-Med Script [Interview], 1967 September 20 (Box 42, Folder 861)
  - "On an Early Genital Phase with an Addendum on Genesis" [Discussion], 1967 October 31 (Box 42, Folder 862)
  - "Observations on Adaptation and Defense InStatu Nascendi: Developmental Precursors in the First Two Years of Life, with Film Illustrations" Georgetown University [Paper], 1967 December 1 (Box 42, Folder 863)
  - "On Human Symbiosis and the Vicissitudes of Individuation" Washington Psychoanalytic and Washington Psychiatric Societies (Joint meeting) [Paper], 1967 December 1 (Box 42, Folder 864)
  - "Observational Data and their Relevance to Psychoanalytic Reconstruction and Prediction" Child Analytic Group Washington Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1967 December 2 (Box 42, Folder 865)
  - "The Pre-Oedipal Determinants of an Infantile Neurosis" by J. B. McDevitt, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1968 January 16 (Box 43, Folder 866)
  - "Observational Data and their Relevance to Psychoanalytic Reconstruction and to Prediction" (with Film Illustration) San Francisco Psychoanalytic Institute Palm Springs [Paper], 1968 February 27, March 2-3 (Box 43, Folder 867)
  - "Observations on Adaptation and Defense InStatu Nascendi: Developmental Precursors in the First Two Years of Life" by M. Mahler, M.D. and J. B. McDevitt, M.D. San Francisco Psychoanalytic Society and Los Angeles Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1968 February 19, 29 (Box 43, Folder 868)
  - "Observational Data and Their Relevance to Psychoanalytic Reconstruction and to Prediction" University of Pittsburgh and Mount Sinai Hospital/Elmhurst Baltimore, MD [Paper], 1968 March 30, April 4, 27 (Box 43, Folder 869)
  - "Reconstruction Paper" Award for Psychoanalytic Education Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1968 May 24 (Box 43, Folder 870)
  - "Observational Data and their Relevance to Psychoanalytic Reconstruction and to Prediction" Norwich, CT [Paper], 1968 September 6 (Box 43, Folder 871)
  - "Remarks About Data on Coanesthetic and Other Pre-Verbal Experiences" Western New England Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1968 September 14 (Box 43, Folder 872)
  - "Separation-Individuation Phase" Discussion Group CG-2 American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1968 December 19 (Box 43, Folder 873)
  - "Today Show" Rockefeller Plaza, RCA Building [Interview], 1969 March 5 (Box 43, Folder 874)
  - "Clinical Studies of the Separation-Individuation Phase" by E. R. Geleerd [Discussion], 1969 March 25 (Box 44, Folder 875-876)
  - "Loss of the Love Object an as Intrapsychic Process" Panel On: Sequelae of Parental Loss American Psychoanalytic Association [Paper], 1969 May 5 (Box 44, Folder 877-878)
  - "Observational Data and Their Relevance for Reconstruction" Long Island Psychoanalytic Society [Paper], 1969 June 3 (Box 44, Folder 879)
  - Dé-Différenciation Perceptuelle et [Relation Objectale] Psychotique, 25:995-1006., 1969 November 7 (Box 44, Folder 880-881)
  - "A Study of the Separation- Individuation Process and its Possible Application to Borderline Phenomena in the Psychoanalytic Situation" Twentieth Freud Anniversary Lecture Academy of Medicine-New York Psychoanalytic Society [Lecture], 1970 March 2-28, undated (Box 45, Folder 882-897)
  - "A Study of the Separation-Individuation Process and its Possible Application to Borderline Phenomena in the Psychoanalytic Situation" Twentieth Freud Anniversary Lecture Academy of Medicine-New York Psychoanalytic Society [Lecture], 1970 February 23-March 1, undated (Box 46, Folder 898-909)
  - Frieda Fromm-Reichmann Award Academy of Psychoanalysis [Paper], 1970 May 9 (Box 47, Folder 910)
  - "Beobachtungen am Saeugling and Seiner Mutter and der Losloesungs-und Individuierungsprozess" Wiener Psychoanalytische Vereinigung [Paper], 1970 May 26 (Box 47, Folder 911)
  - Presentation by Dr. Schiele Child Analysis Meeting Seminar Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute [Discussion], 1970 June 12, 14 (Box 47, Folder 912)
  - "On the Relevance of Observational Data of the Reversal Phase for Reconstruction" First Annual Symposium on Child Development Women's Medical College and Children's Unit, Eastern Pennsylvania Psychiatric Institute [Paper], 1970 June 13 (Box 47, Folder 913)
  - Panel: Review of Psychoanalytic Theory in the Light of Current Research in Child Development" American Psychoanalytic Association [Discussion], 1970 December (Box 47, Folder 914)
  - "The Effects of Object Loss on the Body Image of Schizophrenic Girls" by A. Green, M.D. Association of Psychoanalytic Medicine [Discussion], 1971 January 5 (Box 47, Folder 915)
  - "Notes on the Separation-Individuation Process, with Film Illustrations" Roosevelt Hospital, Grand Rounds [Paper], 1971 January 20 (Box 47, Folder 916)
  - "Development of the Young Child as Expressed Through Bodily Movement" by J. Kestenberg, M.D. New York Psychoanalytic Society [Discussion], 1971 February 23 (Box 47, Folder 917)
  - "Problems in Reconstruction in Child Analysis" by H. Kennedy American Association for Child Psychoanalysis [Discussion], 1971 March 20 (Box 47, Folder 918)
  - "Notes on Reversibility of Later Pathology, with Special Reference to Studies on Separation-Individuation" Council of Psychoanalytic Psychotherapists, Inc. [Paper], 1971 March 28 (Box 47, Folder 919-920)
  - Untitled Center for Advanced Psychological Research (CAPS) [Discussion], 1971 September 17-19 (Box 47, Folder 921)
  - "Danger Signals in the Separation-Individuation Process: The Observations and Formulations of Margaret S. Mahler" by C. Settlage, M.D., and M. Mahler, M.D. San Francisco Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1971 September 22 (Box 48, Folder 922)
  - "Infant Observation and Longitudinal Study, Implications for Mental Health and Primary Prevention of Mental Disorders in High-risk Situations" Academy of Child Psychiatry [Discussion], 1971 October 9 (Box 48, Folder 923)
  - Unknown World Psychiatric Association [Paper], 1971 November 28-December 4 (Box 48, Folder 924)
  - "On the Normal Separation-Individuation Process" American Psychiatric Association [Paper], 1971 December 19 (Box 48, Folder 925)
  - Unknown Child Analysis Study Group Philadelphia Psychoanalytic Institute [Itinerary], 1972 February 17-21 (Box 48, Folder 926)
  - "On the Importance of the Rapprochment Sub-phase of the Separation-Individuation Process" Washington Psychoanalytic Institute [Paper], 1972 April 21 (Box 48, Folder 927)